Guide to the Mrs. Humphry Ward Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Mrs. Humphry Ward collection
1850-1920
GEN MSS 134
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.75
(4 boxes)
The collection consists of miscellaneous letters by Mrs. Humphry Ward and writings, including holographs of The Marriage of William Ashe and A Writer's Recollections.
Ward, Humphry, Mrs., 1851-1920
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ongoing collection of documents acquired by gift and purchase from various sources.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This listing encompasses accessions of single manuscripts and small groups of manuscripts pertaining to Mrs. Humphry Ward acquired by gift or purchase from various sources by the Beinecke Library. Materials acquired prior to January 1995 have been arranged in two series. Series I, Letters, consists of letters by Mrs. Humphry Ward and is alphabetically arranged by recipient. Series II, Writings, contains writings by Mrs. Ward and is arranged alphabetically by title. Materials acquired after January 1995 are located in Series III, Additions since January 1995, and are listed in accession order.
This register is updated periodically. For information on material added to the collection since the last update, please consult the Public Services desk.
Authors, English -- 19th century -- Archives; Women authors -- England; Ward, Humphry, Mrs., 1851-1920
- Letters, 1900 Oct 12; Series I
  - Letter: to Mr. Bridgeman, 1900 Oct 12 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    1 item (2 leaves); 18 cm. ALS. Removed from copy of Marie Clothilde Balfour's From Saranac to the Marquesas and Beyond.
  - Letters to Mr. and Mrs. Capper, 1901, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    2 items. 2 ALS, one (1904 Jan 22) concerning her 'Heresy Trial' letter and Mr. Beeby's resignation. Purchased in 1990.
  - Letter: Villa Canessita, Rapallo, (Italy), to the Drapers' Company., 1901 Mar 27 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    1 item (2 leaves); 21 cm. ALS to the Secretary of the Drapers' Company soliciting a contribution for the Passmore Edwards Settlement. Purchased in 1988.
  - Letter: to Mrs. Field, 1906 Oct 29 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    1 item (2 leaves); 18 cm. ALS concerning proposed visit to the Passmore Edwards Settlement. Purchased in 1994.
  - Letter: Hotel de la Poste, Bérisal, Valais [Switzerland], to Mr. Fitzmaurice, 1899 Jun 26 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    1 item (1 leaf); 20 cm. ALS. Purchased in 1994.
  - Letter: to Miss Gould, 1903 Sep 28 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    1 item (1 leaf); 18 cm. ALS. Purchased in 1995.
  - Letter: to Lord Guthrie, n.y. Mar 23 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letter: to Mrs. [Mary St. Leger Kingsley] Harrison, 1888 Mar 17 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    1 item (2 leaves); 18 cm. ALS expressing admiration for Charles Kingsley. Purchased in 1994.
  - Letters to [Maurice] Hewlett, 1898, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    2 items. 2 ALS, one in praise of The Forest Lovers. Purchased in 1994
  - Letter: to [Robert V.] Johnson, [1905?] Sep 16 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    1 item (2 leaves); 18 cm. ALS. Purchased in 1967.
  - Letter: Villa Pazzi, Arcetri, Florence, to Councillor J. Johnston, 1910 Dec 22 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    1 item (1 leaf); 25 cm. ALS. Purchased in 1994.
  - Letter: to Rev. H. B. Jones, 1903 Jul 3 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    1 item (2 leaves); 18 cm. ALS asking him to conduct services for a Vacation School at the Passmore Edwards Settlement. Purchased in 1988.
  - Letter: to Hughes Massie, 1907 Aug 25 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    1 item (2 leaves); 18 cm. ALS. Purchased in 1988.
  - Letter: to Sir Mountstuart (Grant Duff), 1890 Jan 12 (Box 1, Folder 13a)
    1 item (2 leaves); 18 cm. ALS. Purchased in 1993.
  - Letter: Villa Canessita, [Rapallo, Italy], to Mrs. Pitt, n.y. Apr 6 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    1 item (2 leaves); 18 cm. ALS. Purchased in 1995.
  - Letter: to Lady Richmond, 1904 Mar 5 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Letter: Passmore Edwards Settlement, Tavistock Place, W. C., [London], to Mrs. Thompson, 1915 Oct 28 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    1 item (2 leaves); 25 cm. TLS asking that Mrs. Thompson allow herself to be proposed for election as a member of the Passmore Edwards Settlement. Purchased in 1995.
  - Letter: to "My dear Olive", 1909 Jul 28 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Letter: to "Dear Madam", 1905 Oct 25 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    1 item (2 leaves); 21 cm. ALS declining an invitation to lecture in Lowell. Purchased in 1988.
  - Letter: Hotel Californie, Cannes, Alpes Maritimes [France], to "Dear Sir", 1891 Oct 24 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    1 item (2 leaves); 21 cm. ALS. Purchased in 1994.
  - Letter: to "Dear Sir", 1895 Dec 20 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    1 item (2 leaves); 18 cm. ALS. Purchased in 1994.
- Writings, n.d.; Series II
  - " Helbeck of Bannisdale: Book II, Chapter 4. (The last chapter)," holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 21)
    1 v. (43 l.); 21 cm. Inscribed: "I give this original MS of the last chapter of Helbeck of Bannisdale to the Red Cross Sale 1917. Mary A. Ward." Bound in: ALS from George Meredith thanking Ward for sending him Helbeck of Bannisdale, (2 leaves), 1898 Aug 30. Purchased in 1989.
  - The Marriage of William Ashe
    - Holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 22-35)
      1 item (ca. 590 leaves); 21 cm. and smaller. Original title: "Ashley's Marriage." Purchased in 1989.
    - Page proofs of Chapter 1, corrected, 1903 Nov 1 (Box 1, Folder 36)
      1 item (8 leaves); 19 cm. Stamped: "From Spottiswoode & Co." Purchased in 1989.
    - Page proofs of portions of Part IV, corrected, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 37)
      1 item (32 leaves); 19 cm. Stamped: "From Spottiswoode & Co." Purchased in 1989.
  - Sir George Tressady
    - Holograph and page proof, heavily corrected, [not after 1896] (Box 2, Folder 38-60)
      1 item [ca. 750-800 leaves]; various sizes. Chapters 1-5 fragmentary; 6-23 more complete; 24 in page proof only.
    - Notes and miscellaneous holograph draft pages (Box 3, Folder 61-66)
      1 item [ca. 100 leaves]; various sizes. Purchased in 1990.
    - Page proof, heavily corrected and interleaved with holograph inserts, 1896 (Box 3, Folder 67-70)
      1 item [ca. 200 leaves]; various sizes. Text incomplete. Stamped: "From Spottiswoode & Co." Purchased in 1988.
    - Holograph of a revision of part of Chapter 18, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 71)
      1 item (12 leaves); 21 cm. Purchased in 1988.
    - Miscellaneous holograph pages from a revision, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 72-76)
      1 item [ca. 100 leaves]; various sizes. Purchased in 1988.
    - "Notes on a Staff[ordshire] Visit," holograph, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 77)
      1 item (9 leaves); 20 cm. Possibly research notes for Sir George Tressady. Purchased in 1988.
  - " The War and Elizabeth: Prospectus," holograph and typescript, corrected (Box 3, Folder 78)
    1 item (2 leaves); 26 cm. and smaller. Given in 1972.
  - A Writer's Recollections, holograph, corrected and revised (Box 3, Folder 79-89)
    1 item [ca. 250 leaves]; 26 cm. and smaller. Chapters 1-6 lacking. With: page proof for portion of Chapter 8 (16 leaves). Given in 1972.
  - Notes for an unidentified novel, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 90)
    1 item (21 leaves); 20 cm. Purchased in 1988.
- Additions since January 1995, 1888 Nov 27; Series III
  - Letter: to "Dear Sir", 1888 Nov 27 (Box 4, Folder 91)
    1 item (2 leaves); 18 cm. ALS declining an invitation to lecture on Robert Elsmere. Purchased in 1995.
  - Letter: to "Dear Sir", 1908 Nov 4 (Box 4, Folder 92)
    1 item (1 leaf); 18 cm. ALS declining an invitation by the Royal Society of Medicine. Purchased in 1995.
  - Letter: 25 Grosvenor Place, S. W., to Miss Byham, 1908 Feb 25 (Box 4, Folder 93)
    1 item (2 leaves); 18 cm. ALS declining an invitation to speak on behalf of "Homes for Ladies." Purchased in 1996.
  - Letter: Stocks, Tring, to Madame Blanc, 1906 Jun 27 (Box 4, Folder 94)
    1 item (4 leaves); 18 cm. ALS concerning Ward's health and the critical reception of Fenwick's Career. Purchased in 1997.
  - Letter: Hampden House, Great Missenden, Bucks., to "Sir" (Box 4, Folder 95)
    1 item (2 leaves); 18 cm. ALS concerning a biographical sketch of Ward. Signed: "Mary A. Ward". Purchased in 1997.
  - Photograph: Portrait of Mrs. Humphry Ward, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 96)
  - Letter: Stocks, Tring., to W. Alexander, 1909 Oct 4 (Box 4, Folder 97)
    1 item (2 L); 18 cm. LS (body of letter in third-party hand) concerning Mr. Bok's interview. Signed: "Mary A. Ward." With: envelope. Purchased in 1999.
    Acc #: 990820-g
  - Letter: Stocks, Tring., to Arthur Wagg, 1912 Feb 2 (Box 4, Folder 98)
    1 item (3 L.); 20 cm. ALS concerning Wagg's contribution to the Evening Play Center Fund and her work on their behalf. Tipped onto half sheet of stiff paper. Purchased in 1999.
    Acc #: 990820-h
  - Letter: Stocks, Tring., to Mr. [Vincent] Baddeley, 1911 May 28 (Box 4, Folder 99)
    1 item (2 L.); 18 cm. ALS concerning seats for George V's coronation and the naval review. With: explanatory ANS by Baddeley and a transcript. Purchased in 1999.
    Acc #: 990820-i
  - Letter: 25, Grosvenor Place, to Messrs. Harper, [1899?] (Box 4, Folder 100)
    1 item (6 L.); 18 cm. ALS headed "Private" concerning the forthcoming serial publication of Eleanor, including corrections to the illustrations; also arguing against publication of the novel in 2 volumes in America. Purchased in 2001.
    Acc. #: 20010720-h
  - Fenwick's Career: holograph, draft, with revisions and corrected page proof inserted throughout, [1905-06] (Box 4, Folder 101-121)
    1 item (ca. 350 L); various sizes Chapters I-XIV represented. Purchased in 2001.
    Acc #: 20011204-al
  - Letters to Lady Mirrielees, 1912-13, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 122)
    4 items. 4 ALS to Lady Mirrielees concerning the charitable work done by the British St. Centre for children, inviting her to visit an exhibition of the children's handicrafts, and thanking her for a contribution. Purchased in 2002.
    Acc #: 20020212-e
  - Letter: 61 Russell Square, to "Sir", 1888 Nov 12 (Box 4, Folder 123)
    1 item; 17 cm. ALS insisting that she "did not wish her photograph to be sold to the trade." Annotated in another hand: "Mrs. Ward blows hot and cold... would you write her direct without allusion to me?" Purchased in 2002.
    Acc #: 20020812-m
  - Letters: 25, Grosvenor Place to Mrs. Hugh Smith, 1894, 1895 (Box 4, Folder 124)
    2 items. 2 ALS concerning invitations and visits. Accompanied by typed transcript of 1895 Jun 27 letter. Purchased in 2002.
    Acc #: 20020812-n